Today's דף daf is ע"ו. ayin vav. We start right at the
top of the page and we are continuing talking about the specificities
of the physical way in which the מנחות menachot are made.
So particularly today you'll see it gets very physical and specific. כל
המנחות טעונות שלש מאות שיפה וחמש מאות בעיטה. Kol hamenachot teunot shalosh
meot shifa vechamesh meot beita. All of the מנחות menachot require 300
rubbings and 500 poundings. That's a lot. So the rubbings presumably we're
going to see are going to be at least with the wheat
when you rub the wheat like this in order to get off
the shells. So it doesn't mean I think with every kernel of
wheat, I'm not sure like you have a lot of wheat there
that you're trying to make into flour. So I'm not sure if
you do 300, if you do all the wheat at the same
time, probably can't fit between your hands. Yeah, what you rub it
like this to get off the shells. Anyway, so 300 times you
rub and 500 times when you're making the simple way of reading
this is we'll see in the גמרא Gemara it's 500 times when
you're making the flour, you pound flour as you're making it. Okay,
so that's what you would do. שיפה ובעיטה בחטים. shifa ubeita bechitim.
The משנה Mishna says actually as opposed to what I just said,
שיפה ובעיטה בחטים, shifa ubeita bechitim, that you do the rubbing and
the pounding both with the wheat. So it's not exactly clear to
me the purpose of pounding the wheat, I mean maybe in terms
of turning the kernels into flour, but I don't know if you
would call that pounding, you would grind it, you know, you wouldn't
do like a hand pounding. The way they showed here,
a pestle, you know one of these.
Yeah, maybe. I mean maybe I'm too influenced by רש"י Rashi that
says the pounding is with the fist. Maybe, I mean I never
know בעיטה beita to refer to the way in which you grind
wheat.
You know, is how they showed here, same thing, שיפה shifa and
then בעיטה beita is just pounding it.
Yeah, I know, but you would grind, you wouldn't use a mortar
and pestle.
Then they grind it.
Then you
grind it with a mortar and pestle?
The fist no, the millstone.
So what's the point about beating?
It loosens it up and then this kind of gets it off.
Maybe, okay.
Isn't בעיטה beita a word related to animals that kick?
Yeah, בעיטה beita can mean kicking with the leg, but רש"י Rashi
says based on context it means pounding with the fist. Okay, so
anyway you would do that with the wheat kernels. רבי יוסי אומר,
Rabbi Yosi omer, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says what I was
saying, which is a little more reasonable I think, בבצק. babatze. No,
we're talking about the dough. Now certainly the pounding refers to the
dough. The question is does also the rubbing, maybe you know you'd
rub the dough beforehand. Now what's also fascinating is look at this.
They had a tradition about this 300 and 500 and they had
to, you know, they had this tradition and then the first תנא
Tanna says, oh that was referring to the wheat. And the second
תנא Tanna says no it was referring to the dough. And it's
not like they're basing themselves on any פסוק, pasuk, it's not like
they're basing themselves on any memory on any, you know, tradition of
what actually happened. They had a tradition of this 300 and 500
and they're trying to figure or trying to sort of, you know,
reconstruct what was the context. Was the context the wheat or was
the context the dough?
That's really hard. Like it's a lot of dough, isn't it? Like
you use an עשרון. isaron. How do you manage to like...
first of all, I don't know if it means all at the
same time. I don't know and how about the flour? There was
ten times as much flour, you began with the wheat. You can't
do the rubbing all the wheat at once. So does it mean
all the same time?
Those are big they must have been very difficult. They didn't use
any machine, they used their hand, right? Right, so like, you know.
But you're making like a lot of חלות. challahs. It doesn't mean
you have to make them all at the exact same time.
I remember my grandmother made
this yeast-like cake but it's a little different but it was really
heavy and it was like hard. Took her...
Okay, but then we're going to see in a minute that they
made ten separate חלות challahs or מצות matzahs for each מנחה. mincha.
Each one of them had to be...
so yeah, they divided them into ten. So, you know, they didn't
make one huge thing out of all at once. So maybe that
would help you understand it. That's what I think. I think it's
got to mean combined.
But again what I do think is fascinating is, you know, and
by and I should maybe point that out by, you know, in
terms of also of the structure of the משנה. Mishna. It's often,
you know, scholars have said and it's really quite clear once you
realize it, that, you know, that the later תנאים Tannaim were the
inheritors of earlier משנה, Mishna, which was often very apodictic, very סתם,
stam, very simple. And often what you will find in a משנה
Mishna when you see a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, it's not like
רבי Rebbe first framed the issue in a global statement and then
everybody said their opinion. What it actually was is there was a
tradition of an earlier משנה Mishna and then there was commentary or
debate about what it meant by the later תנאים. Tannaim. So a
great example about this would be the first משנה Mishna in גיטין
Gittin where it says, you know, if you bring a גט get
from חוץ לארץ לארץ ישראל chutz laaretz Eretz Yisrael you have to
say בפני נכתב. bifanai nechtav. And then if you look, there's like
three different תנאים Tannaim who says, here's what חוץ chutz means, here's
what חוץ chutz means, here's what חוץ chutz means. You know, or
מדינת הים. medinat hayam. And they're really explaining that original line in
the משנה. Mishna. So that's probably what's going on here. If you
take a look at the משנה Mishna again, כל המנחות טעונות שלש
מאות שיפה וחמש מאות בעיטה. kol hamenachot teunot shalosh meot shifa vechamesh
meot beita.
That was the tradition. That was the original משנה. Mishna. So then
you had the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that says, right, שיפה ובעיטה
בחטים. shifa ubeita bechitim.
And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says no, what it meant was בבצק.
babatze. Okay, so then you had this tradition of the 300 and
500. The first opinion says it meant at the wheat, and the
second opinion says it means at the dough. Okay, so let's keep
on going. כל המנחות באות עשר עשר חוץ מלחם הפנים. Kol haminachos
ba'os eser eser chutz milechem hapanim. So this helps address Michael's issue
of how do you make this huge amount of dough. All of
the מנחות menachos would come in ten loaves. You would take this
wheat and you would divide or flour you'd divide it into ten
loaves, whether they were loaves or wafers or מצות, matzos, except for
the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, which obviously was twelve because it was,
you know, two columns of six each, that was the שולחן. shulchan.
וחביתי כהן גדול, Vachavittei Kohen Gadol, and the חביתין chavittim of the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol which he brought, you know, half in the
morning half in the afternoon, his regular
מנחה, mincha, שבאות שתים עשרה, sheba'os shtem esrei, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. They came twelve. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara because
they'll make גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah of the חביתין chavittim to the
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and לחם הפנים lechem hapanim clearly is twelve,
it's explicit. Okay, how we know everything else is ten we'll see
in the גמרא, Gemara, but I'll just tell you now that the
תודה, Toda, we learn from the תודה, Toda, the breads of the
תודה Toda that they came in groups of ten. I'll discuss why
in a minute. And we're going to use that as the model.
So that's where the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma gets his opinion, that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda gets his opinion that other than these two,
everything came in loaves of ten. רבי מאיר אומר כולן באות שתים
עשרה. Rabbi Meir omer kulam ba'os shtem esrei. No, you use the
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim as the model, so everything comes in twelve
loaves, חוץ מחלות תודה, chutz mechallos Toda, the חלות תודה challos Toda
everybody agrees is ten, ונזירות, veneziros, and נזיר Nazir שבאות עשר עשר,
sheba'os eser eser, that those come ten. So the question is which
one is the paradigm and which one is the exception? The תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma assumes that the לחמי תודה lachmei Toda is the
rule, ten. The exception is twelve for the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim
and one thing that goes with that, which is the חביתין. chavittim.
And רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the exact opposite. No, the rule
is twelve and the exception is לחמי תודה lachmei Toda which is
ten and one or two things that go with that. Okay, so
there we have, first the way you pound it and make the
dough or the wheat, and then the number of חלות. challos. Let's
look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנא. Tana. שף
אחת בועט שתים. Shaf achas boet shtayim. Now the גמרא, Gemara, now
the ברייתא's Braisa going to tell you how you maintain this three
to five ratio. It's three hundred rubbings and five hundred poundings of
the wheat, or according to the other opinion of the dough. So
here it's going to tell you how you did it. So you
might think you do three and then five, but no, it has
a more inventive way of doing it. שף אחת בועט שתים. Shaf
achas boet shtayim. You do one rubbing and then two poundings. Then
שף שתים בועט שלוש. Shaf shtayim boet shalosh. Then you take the
wheat again, you do two rubbings and then three poundings. You've got
it? So you do one, two, and then one, two, and then
one, two, three. So you've done three rubbings for every five poundings.
Okay, so again and according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma this
is how you would loosen up the shell and the bran from
the wheat. Okay, now בעי רבי ירמיה, Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmiya, so רבי
ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya asks, אמתויי ואתויי חד, Amtuyei ve'atuyei chad, when you're
doing a rubbing, right, how do you do a rubbing? You go
like this, right, you go like this. So he says, how do
you count? Does this count as one, this count as two, or
does back and forth count as one? Because you know, you've got
to do your three hundred rubbings so you want to know how
to count them. אמתויי ואתויי חד, Amtuyei ve'atuyei chad, is back and
forth count as one,
או דילמא אמתויי ואתויי תרי, o dilma amtuyei ve'atuyei tary, back and
forth counts as two? מאי, Mai, what's the הלכה? halacha? תיקו. Teiku.
So the גמרא Gemara has this question, it comes up in a
number of different contexts where
it talks about doing certain things back and forth and X number
of times. He also always wants to know is back and forth
count as two or count as one. Okay, so anyway, that's the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that the three hundred and the five hundred
rubbings and poundings was with the was with the grain, was with
the, I keep on saying, well wheat, it normally used wheat. That's,
yeah, right, no, I'm saying but the עומר omer it's barley but
we're off the עומר. omer. Anyway, with the grain. And then you
have the other opinion that says it's with the dough. רבי יוסי
אומר בבצק. Rabbi Yossi omer bebatzeik. No, no, no, you did the
rubbing and the pounding with the dough, not with the grain. So
the גמרא Gemara says, שיפה ובעיטה בחיטין, Shifah u've'itah bechittim, I'm sorry,
skip a line. No, שיפה ובעיטה בחיטין, Shifah u've'itah bechittim, רבי יוסי
אומר בבצק, Rabbi Yossi omer bebatzeik, with the dough. איבעיא להו, Ibeiya
lehu, they raised the question, בבצק ולא בחיטין, bebatzeik velo bechittim,
is he saying you only did it in the dough and you
didn't do it on the wheat? או דילמא אף בבצק, o dilma
af bebatzeik, he says no, I agree with you it was on
the wheat, but they also did the three hundred and five hundred
in the dough. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, דתניא, detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, שיפה ובעיטה בחיטין, shifah u've'itah bechittim,
the rubbing and the pounding was with the wheat. רבי יוסי אומר
שיפה ובעיטה בבצק. Rabbi Yossi omer shifah u've'itah bebatzeik. No, it was
with the dough. So because it gives the only way there's a
difference in our משנה Mishnah is he repeats the verbs שיפה ובעיטה,
shifah u've'itah, which is somehow emphasizing, I'm not adding to you, no,
no, this is the way it was, it was שיפה ובעיטה shifah
u've'itah was with the dough. Now if you look so it's only
the dough, not with the grain. If you look at the side
however, we have a different גרסא. girsa. If you look at the
left hand column, נוסח אחר, nusach acher, like right there, you know,
at the far left hand, שיפה בחיטין ובעיטה בבצק, shifah bechittim u've'itah
bebatzeik, וכן משמע
ברמב"ם. vechein mashma baRambam. So that's an interesting third opinion which probably
makes the most logical sense. The rubbing is with the wheat, that's
the way you get off the shell, and the pounding is with
the dough, because that's how you make dough, right? You roll and
then you pound it. Okay, so it makes even for a third
opinion. But again, what I think is fascinating is nobody is getting
it from a פסוק, pasuk, nobody is getting it from a remembered,
you know, memory. They all have a tradition of this line of
three hundred and
five hundred, that's the...
You could do all three ways.
Right. You know, we could do that at the end for our
סיום, Siyum, right though? Make a note here.
We could have all tables set out like activities for the סיום.
Siyum. Try to make your own מצה, Matzah, try to make... okay.
So now it says like this. כל המנחות באות, Kol hamenachos ba’os,
okay, עשר עשר eser eser except these which are שתים עשרה. shtayim
esreh. So the first opinion is normal מנחות Menachos are ten loaves,
except with the exception of the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim and the
חביתין Chavitin which are twelve. Oh,
whoops. Oh my God, I think I just... I forgot to turn
on the mic. Jed, sorry, the mic is now on. I hope
you're still on. Okay.
All right, sorry about that Jed. First 15 minutes without the audio.
כל המנחות באות שתים עשרה. Kol hamenachos ba’os shtayim esreh. לחם הפנים
והחביתין. Lechem Hapanim vehachavitin. לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim it says explicitly that
12 obviously because it was you know six in each column that's
explicit in the תורה. Torah. חביתי כהן גדול, Chaviti Kohen Gadol, how
about the חביתין? Chavitin? אתיא חוקה חוקה מלחם הפנים. Asya chukka chukka
mi-Lechem Hapanim. So there's a גזירה שוה Gezeirah shavah from the לחם
הפנים Lechem Hapanim because by לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim it says חוק.
chok. I'll read you the פסוק Pasuk and by the and by
the חביתין Chavitin it says חוק, chok, I'll read you the פסוק
Pasuk in Rashi. חוק עולם לה' כליל תקטר Chok olam la-Hashem kalil
tuktar is what it says by the חביתין. Chavitin. And by לחם
הפנים Lechem Hapanim it says קדש קדשים הוא לו מאשי ה' חוק
עולם. Kodesh kodashim hu lo me-ishei Hashem chok olam. So the חוק
חוק chok chok is the גזירה שוה, Gezeirah shavah, so we learn
12 and 12. That's the one thing we learn from the לחם
הפנים Lechem Hapanim is the חביתין Chavitin comes 12.
Now כל המנחות דבאות עשר עשר מנלן? Kol hamenachos de-ba'os eser eser
minalan? Okay, so that's the one thing we learn from the לחם
הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. But how do you know the general rule of
10? גמר מלחמי תודה. Gamar mi-lachmei Todah. We learn it from the
breads of the תודה. Todah. מה להלן עשר אף כאן עשר. Mah
le-halan eser af kan eser. The same way there each type of
bread came ten, here too each type of bread came ten. Now
how do we know that that was true there? Because there it
says that you take one of the loaves of each type. It
says you bring four types of loaves, you bring חמץ, Chametz, you
bring three types of מצה, Matzah, לחם, רקיקים, lechem, rekikim, whatever, you
bring three types of מצה Matzah and it says you take one
of each type and you give it to the כהן. Kohen. The
way the תורה Torah says you take one of each type is
as you should take one תרומה, Terumah, a gift to the כהן.
Kohen. תרומה Terumah is often a word that's used for something that
you lift up, you separate out for a gift. However, we do
have תרומה Terumah one of the places תרומה Terumah appears is תרומת
מעשר. Terumas Ma'aser. When the לויים Levi'im take from their own מעשר
Ma'aser and they give a portion of their מעשר Ma'aser to the
כהן, Kohen, it calls it a תרומה, Terumah, but the תורה Torah
also says explicitly that is a tenth,
מעשר מן המעשר. ma'aser min ha-ma'aser. So there תרומה Terumah explicitly means
one tenth. Now it is true תרומה Terumah sometimes means much less.
The normal תרומה Terumah for ישראל, Yisrael, the way חז"ל Chazal said
it, it's about 1/50th or 1/60th, okay, 1/40th, whatever it might be.
But nevertheless because there you know from they were assuming that you're
not making 50 loaves, so חז"ל Chazal understood and they needed to
get a number, they basically understood that there the תרומה Terumah meant
the context of one tenth. So from the very idea of לחמי
תודה lachmei Todah is itself not explicit, but because the תורה Torah
uses the phrase תרומה Terumah of the one loaf of each type
you give to the כהן, Kohen, they understand that that means that
there were ten loaves of each type. Once there were ten loaves
of each type by the תודה, Todah, now we're going to use
that as a model for all the מנחות. Menachos. מה להלן עשר,
Mah le-halan eser, the same way there there was ten, אף כאן
עשר, af kan eser, here too there's also ten.
And if you use the same quantity of grain, but you make
them into bigger loaves, would that be possible?
Same quantity of grain. Oh so we're going to talk about the
בדיעבד bedi'eved later in a minute. The בדיעבד bedi'eved is coming up.
Most of these things as we mentioned yesterday, it's going to be
a later משנה, Mishnah, but all of these things about at what
stage you put the oil and how you do it, like בדיעבד
bedi'eved you're יוצא yotzei even without that. Okay, although it does raise
an interesting question about, you know, since the תורה Torah does describe
them as physically different, there's got to be a certain stage in
which you can't call this thing anymore like a חביתין Chavitin if
it didn't have, you know, if the oil was done in a
way that it didn't actually have the same physical character. But anyway
most of these specific details are not מעכב בדיעבד. me'akev bedi'eved. I'm
speculating but I'm saying you have to imagine that there's a point
at which it's no longer the thing itself. But most of these
specific details are not מעכב בדיעבד. me'akev bedi'eved. We're going to talk
in a minute, certainly the 300 and the 500 poundings nobody thinks
is מעכב. me'akev. We're going to talk in a minute about the
number of loaves, okay, that's going to come up. Okay, so let's
take a look. Okay, so מה להלן עשר אף כאן עשר. Mah
le-halan eser af kan eser. ולילף מלחם הפנים? Veyelef mi-Lechem Hapanim? So
the גמרא Gemara basically asks a very reasonable question. We have two
models. לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim is 12, לחמי תודה lachmei Todah is
10. How do you decide which is your rule and which is
your exception? Why is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah assuming make the לחמי
תודה lachmei Todah your rule and say everything is ten? Why not
make לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim your rule and say everything is 12?
מה להלן שתים עשרה אף כאן שתים עשרה? Mah le-halan shtayim esreh
af kan shtayim esreh? Why not say that the
לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim is the rule? That's 12, everything should be
12. So it says no. מסתברא מלחמי תודה הוי ליה למילף, Mistavra
mi-lachmei Todah havah leih lemilaf, it makes more sense to learn from
לחמי תודה. lachmei Todah. שכן, Shekein, and now we're going to do
as you're familiar with what the גמרא Gemara does, it makes the
number of the number of points of comparison, the number of ways
in which the characteristics are similar, so it should serve as the
logical model. So in what way is a normal מנחה Mincha similar
to
the לחמי תודה? Lachmei Todah? Let's take a look. שכן יחיד, Shekein
yachid, so a normal מנחה Mincha and לחמי תודה Lachmei Todah obviously
are coming as an individual קרבן, korban, as opposed to the לחם
הפנים Lechem Hapanim which is the ציבור tzibur קרבן, korban, the communal
קרבן. korban. המתנדב, Hamitnadeiv, it comes through a vow as opposed to
the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim which is an obligation, it's not on
the basis of a vow. שמן, Shemen, they both have oil, right?
The לחמי תודה Lachmei Todah are baked with oil, excuse me, the
לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim is baked without
oil.
Every way I mean no שמן shemen essentially, right?
No, both of these have oil in contrast to the... this is
the way in which a normal מנחה Mincha is similar to לחמי...
similar to לחמי תודה. Lachmei Todah.
Okay, they all have oil. לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim has no oil,
it's just plain bread. Okay. שלא בשבת, Shelo b'Shabbos, you don't... it
doesn't override שבת Shabbos as opposed to the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
which is brought on שבת, Shabbos, so clearly overrides שבת. Shabbos. It's
a ציבור tzibur and a fixed time. שלא בטומאה, Shelo b'tumah, you
wouldn't do it in טומאה. tumah. Again, these are reflections of the
other differences. It's not a communal and it's not a fixed time
as opposed to the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim which is communal and
a fixed time. So it has all those points of comparison and
therefore we should learn out the normal מנחה Mincha from the לחמי
תודה. Lachmei Todah.
Again, this is just... one is really only two. I know.
All right, but the גמרא Gemara does that. אדרבה, Adrabah, the גמרא
Gemara says the opposite. מלחם הפנים הוי ליה למילף, Mi-Lechem Hapanim havay
lei l'meilaf, no, I should say use לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim as
your model for normal מנחות Minachos and learn out from that. Why?
Here are the ways in which normal מנחות Minachos are similar to
לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim and different from לחמי תודה. Lachmei Todah... שכן
הקדש, Shekein hekdesh, now they're both obviously קדוש, kadosh, but they're קדש
קדשים. kodesh kodashim. Remember לחמי תודה... Lachmei Todah. a מנחה Mincha is
קדש קדשים, kodesh kodashim, it's eaten by the כהנים Kohanim in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But the one exception to this we don't
normally pay attention to is the לחמי תודה. Lachmei Todah There you
have bread that is coming to accompany a קרבן, korban, but what
type of קרבן? korban? A קרבן korban that's a שלמים, Shelamim, that's
קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, that's eaten by the owners outside of the
מקדש Mikdash in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So that bread as well is eaten
as קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, is eaten outside the מקדש Mikdash in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So that's an interesting phenomenon we haven't thought about yet.
That is the one case in which you have a type of
a bread or מנחה Mincha that comes in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash that is קדשים קלים kodashim kalim is the bread that comes
with the תודה. Todah. So in that way we should learn out
from... what?
Do the כהנים Kohanim eat all that bread?
No, the כהנים Kohanim get one out of every ten loaves, the
בעלים be'alim eat the rest. Okay, so שכן הקדש, Shekein hekdesh, so
the way in which a normal מנחה Mincha is similar to the
לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim is that they're both קדש קדשים kodesh kodashim
and therefore לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim should be your model. לבונה, Levonah,
both לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim and normal מנחות Minachos have לבונה. Levonah.
The לחמי תודה Lachmei Todah don't, the לחמי תודה Lachmei Todah, are
just accompanying the קרבן, korban, they don't have any לבונה. Levonah. מצה,
Matzah, they all come... not חמץ chametz as opposed to the לחמי
תודה, Lachmei Todah, ten of the loaves of the תודה Todah are
חמץ. chametz. ועצם, Ve'etzem, it doesn't mean bone, it means עצמו, atzmo,
they're coming on their own sake, right? A normal מנחה Mincha and
the לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim, they themselves are the קרבן. korban. But
the לחמי תודה, Lachmei Todah. they're just the accompaniment for the animal
which is the real קרבן. korban. So therefore, better to learn out
from the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim that has these points of comparison
rather than from the לחמי תודה. Lachmei Toda So the גמרא Gemara
says no, הנהו נפישין. hanehu nefishin. The first list was more, the
first list I think was five, this is four, whatever, so therefore
we go by the first list. Okay, now we're going to have
another question. ואי סבירא לן דבר הלמד בגזירה שוה חוזר ומלמד בבנין
אב, V'ee sevira lan davar ha-lamed b'gezeirah shavah chozer u-melamed b'binyan av,
remember that from זבחים? Zevachim? Whether you can do that after you
made one learning could you learn out another thing? So if you
think that something was learned from a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, what
was learned from a גזירה שוה? gezeirah shavah? The חביתין Chavitin of
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. The חביתין Chavitin of the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol was the one thing based on חוקה חוקה chukah chukah
that we know you brought twelve from the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
So now saying look, I understand you don't want to learn out
from לחם הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim is you know
it's a communal קרבן, korban, it's not an individual קרבן. korban. But
I'm going to finesse it because לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim teaches me
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Now let's use כהן גדול Kohen Gadol as
the model. כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has twelve and that's a better
model to learn the other מנחות Minachos from, that's a personal individual
קרבן. korban. And but that assumes that something learned מאי mi גזירה
שוה, gezeirah shavah, I learned כהן גדול Kohen Gadol from a גזירה
שוה gezeirah shavah from לחם הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. Now I can be
חוזר ומלמד בבנין אב. chozer u-melamed b'binyan av. Now I can use
that as a model, as a paradigm, to teach about other cases.
So if we can assume that, that although I learned it from
a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah I can now use it to teach
other cases, let's learn from the case of the חביתין Chavitin of
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the חביתין Chavitin of the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol which is more similar to a normal מנחה. Mincha. נילף,
Neileif, let's learn, מחביתי כהן גדול. m'Chavitei Kohen Gadol. מה להלן שתים
עשרה אף כאן שתים עשרה, Ma halan sheteim esre af kan sheteim
esre, the same way there it's twelve, here too it's twelve. No,
מסתברא מלחמי תודה הוי ליה למילף. Mistavra mi-Lachmei Todah havay lei l'meilaf.
Still, the bread of the תודה Todah is a better model, a
better paradigm, than that of the חביתין Chavitin of the כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. Why? שכן, Shekein, here again are the points of comparison
of a normal מנחה... Mincha... From a מנחה Mincha to a לחמי
תודה Lachmei Toda and a way in which it's different from a
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So you can't say individual, they're both individual.
Okay, but here are the differences. הדיוט, Hedyot, so not יחיד Yachid
but הדיוט, Hedyot, a layperson, right, a normal מנחה Mincha and לחמי
תודה Lachmei Toda are brought by laypeople as opposed to כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is only brought by the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. שנדבה,
She'nidva, it comes through a vow, a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol comes
through an obligation, his מנחה. Mincha. חצאים, Chatza'im, this here it means
not half, they don't come in halves, a normal מנחה Mincha and
לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda. you bring as one whole unit, the כהן
גדול's Kohen Gadol מנחה Mincha is split half in the morning and
half in the afternoon. לפיגול, L'pigul,
they both can become פיגול Pigul because, you know, remember our friend
פיגול, Pigul, right, you're מקריב Makriv the קומץ Kometz and you have
a פיגול Pigul thought. So that can happen by לחמי תודה. Lachmei
Toda, When do you have your פיגול Pigul thought? When you're throwing
the blood of the קרבן, Korban, that's sort of the מתיר Matir
of the לחמי תודה, Lachmei Toda there you could have your פיגול
Pigul thought. You could have your פיגול Pigul thought by a normal
מנחה Mincha when you're doing the קומץ. Kometz. Why can't you have
a פיגול Pigul thought by the מנחה Mincha of a כהן גדול?
Kohen Gadol? Because the מנחה Mincha of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
doesn't have a מתיר, Matir, you burn the whole thing. פיגול Pigul
requires that I'm doing using object one to permit object two. So
when I'm doing the מתיר, Matir, I'm throwing the blood to permit
the meat, then I have my פיגול Pigul thought and it affects
the meat. If I burn everything like the מנחה Mincha of the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, since I'm since there's not I'm doing A
and that permits B, it's just all going straight up, I can't
a פיגול Pigul thought would not be effect.
They can only, you know, mess it up procedurally but not
the, yeah, quote unquote in your mind intentionally.
I mean, לא לשמה Lo lishmah could still be an issue, but
you know, the לאו לביא למן לשם חובה Lav l'vai l'man l'shem
chova and so on, but right, פיגול Pigul is not a problem.
פיגול Pigul needs there to be a מתיר. Matir. This doesn't have
a מתיר. Matir. So again in that way it's different than the
חביתין Chavitin of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. You can have פיגול
Pigul and שלא בשבת ושלא בטומאה Shelo b'Shabbat v'shelo b'tuma because תודה
Toda and a normal מנחה Mincha are personal קרבנות Korbanot and they're
not fixed time, they don't override שבת Shabbat and טומאה Tuma as
opposed to the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol קרבן Korban does override שבת
Shabbat and it would override טומאה. Tuma. So therefore those are the
ways in which why we should be learning out from a normal,
from a לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda, and not from כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. But the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה, Adaraba, no, opposite, מחביתי כהן
גדול הוי ליה למילף. Me'chavitei Kohen Gadol hava leh lemeilaf.
Now that I've moved away from the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim and
I'm to the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, there's it's that's a much
stronger model to learn out from the חביתין Chavitin of the כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. Why? שכן, Sheken, here are the points of comparison:
עישרון, Issaron, both what the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings and a
normal מנחה Mincha is an עישרון, Issaron, is you know whatever that
quantity of flour, as opposed to a תודה, Toda, תודה Toda you
bring, you know you'll see in the next משנה, Mishna, you bring
a lot of flour for a תודה, Toda, much more than an
עישרון. Issaron. Okay, so therefore it's not similar in terms of the
amount of flour. כלי, Kli, you would use a vessel. Now what
does that mean that you would use a vessel? I mean, you'd
use a holy vessel, a כלי שרת Kli sharet for both of
them. So let me just double check רש״י, Rashi, hold on, how
רש״י Rashi explains, hold on.
Oh right, so all of them you would use a כלי שרת,
Kli sharet, but the לחמי תודה, Lachmei Toda, their full קדושה Kedusha
would come when you slaughter the קרבן. Korban. Okay, if you remember
by a מנחה Mincha it's always this issue as opposed to an
animal that when you immediately sanctify an animal you give it full
קדושת הגוף. Kedushat haguf. Okay, by a מנחה Mincha somehow it needs
something else to give it the קדושה, Kedusha, we often talk about
the קדושה Kedusha of the כלי שרת. Kli sharet. But when you
bring a מנחה Mincha together with a קרבן, Korban, like the עומר
Omer that comes the שתי הלחם Shtei halechem that comes with the
כבשי עצרת Kivsei Atzeret or, you know, the what do you call
it, the תודה Toda that comes with the animal and that the
slaughtering of the animal is the הקרבה Hakrava that you're doing, in
that case is you need the slaughtering of the animal to give
the full קדושה Kedusha to the מנחה. Mincha. Okay, so in that
way לחמי תודה, Lachmei Toda it's not all through the vessel, it's
also through the slaughtering of the animal. הקדש, Hekdesh, both חביתי כהן
גדול Chavitei Kohen Gadol and normal מנחה Mincha are קודש קדשים Kodesh
kadashim as opposed to לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda which is like the
תודה, Toda, קדשים קלים. Kadashim kalim. ולבונה, V'levona, both have לבונה Levona
because they are both being brought on their own accord as opposed
to the לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda which are just the accompaniment. מצה,
Matza, they're both מצה, Matza, לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda ten loaves are
חמץ. Chametz. ועצמן, V'atzman, they come on their own accord, the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol and a normal מנחה Mincha as opposed to לחמי
תודה Lachmei Toda which are accompanying the קרבן. Korban. הגשה, Hagasha, because
they're coming on their own accord they have a lot of other
points of comparison: הגשה, Hagasha, you touch the מנחה Mincha to the
מזבח. Mizbeach. ואישים, V'ishim, and actually you burn some of the מנחה
Mincha on the fire, both by the חביתי כהן גדול Chavitei Kohen
Gadol and by the normal מנחה Mincha and again as opposed to
the לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda which are just accompanying the animal and
do not do הגשה Hagasha and you don't burn it on the
fire. והנך נפישן, V'hanach nefishen, and these are this is a much
longer list.
So now if we've gotten it to the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
we really should learn twelve because the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is
a much better model. So the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה, Adaraba, no,
nevertheless, הדיוט מהדיוט עדיף ליה. Hedyot m'hedyot adif leh. Even though it's
a longer list, it's still the idea that they're both lay קרבנות
Korbanot is more persuasive as serving as the model, that a כהן
גדול's Kohen Gadol קרבן Korban or the קרבן Korban of a ציבור
Tzibbur will will assume that those are exceptions. And therefore what we're
going to choose for a model will be
if we... what we find as a קרבן korban of a lay
individual. And that's why, that's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says, so again where are we? כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
and well
לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim is explicit. From there we learn out כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol is 12. תודה Toda we learn out is 10.
And which serves as the model? And in the end we're saying
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda chooses the model of the לחמי תודה Lachmei
Toda? because that is a lay person's קרבן. korban. And for him
that is the better model. So אף על גב Af al gav
we started saying right before a few lines before we started getting
lines. מה להלן עשרה אף כאן עשרה Ma le'halan asara af kan
asara then וניהדר וניילף מלחם הפנים Venehadar veneilef mi'Lechem Hapanim because yeah
you could have just gone
straight to the end.
You could have just gone straight to the end and said משום
דהני נפישי mishum de'hani nefishei because we don't end up saying that
really. Right, well, only if you have to say דבר הלמד בגזירה
שוה davar ha'lamed be'gezeirah shavah and so on. So right, but you
could have jumped to the end.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. And
how about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
learns 12, who says 12, takes the opposite approach. Says we're going
to learn from לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim or from the כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. So
what does he say? אמר כולם בשתים עשרה. Amar kulam be-shteim esrei.
It's 12. That the model is the לחם הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. מאי
קסבר? Mai kasavar? What does he hold? So now we're going to
basically do his sort of in reverse of how we just did
the other. But don't worry it'll be short. אי סבירא ליה דבר
הלמד בגזירה שוה חוזר ומלמד בבנין אב. Ei sevira lei davar ha'lamed
be'gezeirah shavah chozer u'melamed be'binyan av. If he holds that something you
learn from a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, i.e., the חביתין Chavitin of
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you can then use to be a
paradigm and to teach other cases, then it's easy. So therefore ניילף
מחביתי כהן גדול, neilef me-Chavitei Kohen Gadol, then he'll use כהן גדול's
Kohen Gadol קרבן korban as his model, דהני נפישי de'hani nefishei because
there's many more points of comparison as we just got through saying.
So if כהן, kohen. if you have the option of using the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol it makes sense why רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
would say that's going to be my model. That is many more
points of comparison with a normal מנחה, mincha, that will serve as
my model that you bring 12. Now even if that's not true,
אי סבירא ליה ei sevira lei and if he held דדבר הלמד
בגזירה שוה אינו חוזר ומלמד בבנין אב, de'davar ha'lamed be'gezeirah shavah eino
chozer u'melamed be'binyan av, you can't learn from כהן גדול kohen gadol,
because it was learned from a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. Why does
he prefer to learn from לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim rather than לחמי
תודה? Lachmei Toda לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda would seem a little bit
more similar. Nevertheless, ניילף מלחם הפנים, neilef mi'Lechem Hapanim, he'd rather learn
from לחם הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. הקדש מהקדש עדיף ליה. hekdesh me-hekdesh adif
lei. Although the other one said I'd rather learn from a lay
קרבן korban to a lay קרבן, korban, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir could
say I'd rather learn from קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim from קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. A normal מנחה mincha is קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, לחם
הפנים Lechem Hapanim is קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. To me that's much
more of an important point of comparison than to לחמי תודה Lachmei
Toda which are קדשים קלים kodashim kalim and maybe have a totally
different status. You could also have said to me also the point
is from לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda which are an accompaniment and are
not brought on their own, on their own, on their own. I'd
rather learn from something that's brought as its own קרבן korban to
something that's brought as its own קרבן. korban. So here you have
the debate whether it's 10 or 12. Okay and now we are
going to have the last point of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that
if he says the basic rule is 12, what is the cases
that he admits are 10? חוץ מלחמי תודה ונזירות דאתין עשר עשר.
Chutz mi'Lachmei Toda u'Nezirut de'atyan esar esar. That is the one case,
two cases that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir will admit do come as
10 is לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda and נזירות. Nezirut. לחמי תודה בהדיא
כתיב ביה. Lachmei Toda be'hedya ketiv bei. לחמי תודה Lachmei Toda. it
says explicitly. You gotta love the way the גמרא Gemara says בהדיא
כתיב ביה be'hedya ketiv bei when we learn it out from the
word תרומה. terumah. But okay, meaning that's an established דרשה, drasha, we
all know that, it's as if, if that's what the word means,
then it's written explicitly. Okay. So נזירות, Nezirut, how do we know
נזירות? Nezirut? דאמר מר de'amar mar because we have a teaching that
we learn נזירות Nezirut from into the פסוקים psukim by לחמי תודה.
Lachmei Toda שלמיו shlamav because it says by the לחמי תודה lachmei
Todah you should bring it על זבח תודת שלמיו al zevach todat
shlamav on his slaughtering of the תודה Toda of his שלמים. shlamim.
And the word שלמים shlamim there is extra. Could have just said
על זבח התודה. al zevach ha-toda. So why does it say תודת
שלמיו todat shlamav when it talks about a תודה? Toda? לרבות שלמי
נזיר, lerabot Shlamei Nazir, it's including even the שלמים shlamim of a
נזיר nazir that we learn a lot of things from the way
a תודה Toda is brought and one of the things that's relevant
to us is that we learn that the breads that come with
the נזיר, nazir, that's explicit by the שלמים shlamim of a נזיר,
nazir, but we learn that the תודה Toda serves as the model.
So how much flour you use and whether and the fact that
here that you come, you bring it as 10 loaves. Okay, so
that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir rule is 12,
his exception is 10, as opposed to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda whose
rule is 10 and the exception is 12. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara says, now we, now that we've established those positions, we're going
to talk about what if you didn't do it exactly this way?
אמר רב טובי בר קיסנא, Amar Rav Tuvi bar Kisna, אמר שמואל
amar Shmuel in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, לחמי תודה שאפאן ארבע
חלות יצא. Lachmei Toda she-afan arba chalot yatza. You didn't do your
40, you're supposed to do 10 of each genre, and instead of
doing 10 of each genre, you have to have four separate types,
but you basically do four huge חלות. chalot. Like your grandma. Okay.
So there you do all four types but rather than 10 of
each type you do one of each type. It's the full amount
of flour but it's a huge loaf of bread and it's really
huge because we're going to see in the next משנה Mishna how
much flour you use for a תודה Toda which was an enormous
amount. Okay. So what's the הלכה? halacha? He says you're יצא, yotzei,
בדיעבד be'di'avad you don't need it. 10 is the לכתחילה, le'chat'chila, בדיעבד
be'di'avad you don't need it. דלא כמו לחם הפנים לעיכובא D'lo k'mo
Lechem Hapanim le'ikuva though. Right, well we're going to talk about that,
that's coming up. והא בעינן ארבעים? Ve-ha ba'inan arba'im? Don't we have
a principle that we learn four types... And we learned ten loaves
and they're forty loaves? למצוה. L'mitzvah. That's לכתחילה l'chatchila by so many
things about קרבנות, korbanot, if we don't know, if the תורה Torah
doesn't tell us it's מעכב, me'akev, we assume it's only a לכתחילה.
l'chatchila. והא בעיא אפרושי תרומה מינייהו, V'ha ba'ya afrushi teruma mineihu, now
we got another problem. Fine, the number could be a מצוה. mitzvah.
But it says take one of the loaves of each type and
give it to the כהן.
kohen How could you take
one of the loaves of each type if you only have one
loaf of each type? Right? And you can't say I'll give it
all to the כהן kohen, because then it's not a תרומה. teruma.
תרומה teruma means you're separating one thing from the rest. So what
are you going to give to the כהן, kohen. right? So now,
maybe you give them a piece of the loaf. Okay. But the
גמרא Gemara is going to say that can't work. וכי תימא דמפריש
מכל חד וחד, V'chi teima d'mafrish mikol chad v'chad, and maybe you
break off a piece from every one of your huge loaves. אחד
Echad אמר רחמנא, amar Rachmana, it says you give one as a
תרומה teruma לכהן, l'kohen, and from that אחד echad we learn it
means a full, a complete one, שלא יטול פרוס, shelo yitol paros,
that you can't give him a broken off piece. So how can
you do this? How can you make like those like breakaways? Okay,
well that's essentially what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. Let's take
a look. דאפרשינהו בלישה. D'afrishinhu b'lisha. You separated it off when you
were actually kneading the dough. So you're making a huge loaf and
you separate off a little piece and you bake that separately and
that's going to be what you're going to give to the כהן.
kohen But then of course it's no longer four loaves, it's eight
loaves. Right. So it's not exactly explicit in the גמרא. Gemara. The
רש״י Rashi here was a little ambiguous
and I thought he
was trying to say something like Michael just said, like a type
of a breakaway. Like exactly that, you separate it and then you
bake them next to each other and maybe something like that and
it's still, but anyway this גמרא's Gemara quoted elsewhere and the מפרשים
mefarshim elsewhere say that you literally do bake them separately. But then
it's not four loaves anymore, then it's eight loaves. Okay, but forty.
Right, now forty. Right. Why doesn't the גמרא Gemara also answer here
למצוה? l'mitzvah? You mean how do you know when it says that
the אחד echad means, maybe the whole idea of אחד ולא פרוס
echad v'lo paros is also למצוה? l'mitzvah? Yeah, it's a good question.
You know, when the גמרא Gemara decides to assume that something is
מעכב me'akev or not. I mean, if you ask me I would
say that it's because it's not the, you know, when it has
to do with like the identity of the thing, it's not the
thing itself, then you can't just say it's a מצוה. mitzvah.
It's sort of like, you know, for example, I don't
know if this is true, I'd have to check it. When the
תורה Torah says, you know, that an עולה olah can only come
from a זכר zachar and it has to be a certain age.
Do we assume that it has to repeat it? And if it
doesn't repeat it, it's not מעכב? me'akev? Or do we assume that
when you're describing the basic like identity of the object, then if
it's not that thing then it's something else? You know, normally the
למצוה l'mitzvah has to do with like a specific of the ritual,
not about the identity of the object. So that's sort of intuitively
what I would say here. If you're saying that what you give
a כהן kohen, is a whole loaf, then something else is like
a different object. That's off the top of my head. All right,
appreciate it. It's also like I said to Michael before about we're
going to learn a later משנה Mishnah that says if you don't
do all the oil things in the exact right way, you're still
יוצא. yotzei. But let's say you do it so different that it's
a different type of a physical thing. Then presumably it's no longer
the thing itself. Okay. So מיתיבי. Meitivei. So I'm going to ask
you on this. So in principle you're saying that the number is
not מעכב. me'akev. You got to solve the problem about how do
you give the one to the כהן, but in principle the number
is not מעכב. me'akev.
I'm going to ask you on this.
Here's a ברייתא. braita. כל המנחות שריבה במידת חלתן או שמיעט במידת
חלתן כשרות. Kol haminachot sheriba bemidat challatan o shemi'eit bemidat challatan k'sherot.
Any מנחות menachot that you have more loaves of bread, more than
the ten, or fewer, less than the ten, it's still כשרה. kshera.
So the number is not מעכב me'akev in most cases. Okay, that's
only למצוה l'mitzvah like so many other things. חוץ מלחם הפנים וחביתי
כהן גדול, Chutz milechem hapanim vachavitei kohen gadol, except for the לחם
הפנים lechem hapanim and the חביתים chavitim of the כהן גדול, which
are twelve. Why? So presumably, and תוספות Tosafot says this, because there
it says חוקה. chuka. The whole גזירה שוה gezeira shava was חוקה
תחוק. chuka techok. חוק Chok is a word that the גמרא Gemara
says means that it has to be exactly this way. So and
also in particular the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, how could you do
it if it's not twelve? If it's more than twelve, where are
you going to put it? The extras. And if it's not twelve,
you're not filling up the שלחן. shulchan. So anyways those have to
be twelve. That is מעכב. me'akev. Okay? Now, but the ברייתא braita
then goes on, two other things that's מעכב. me'akev. דלחמי תודה ונזירות.
D'lachmei Todah u'Nezirut. דלחמי תודה ונזירות, D'lachmei Todah u'Nezirut, presumably because there
it says ten explicitly. It either says explicitly by לחמי תודה lachmei
Todah or we have a פסוק pasuk to learn out נזירות, Nezirut,
and as opposed to all the other cases where we just use
it as a paradigm and by analogy, by לחמי תודה lachmei Todah.
the way the גמרא Gemara understands it explicitly says ten. So this
ברייתא braita says you can't compromise on the ten of לחמי תודה.
lachmei Todah. So you're going against this ברייתא. braita. Other things you
can do more or less than ten, but not לחמי תודה. lachmei
Todah? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. הוא דאמר, Hu
d'amar, no, שמואל Shmuel says why? כי האי תנא, Ki hai tanna,
like the following תנא. tanna. דתניא, D'tanya, you're right, it's a debate.
Can you have fewer than ten for the לחמי תודה? lachmei toda?
דתניא D'tanya we taught in a ברייתא, braita, כל המנחות שריבה במידת
חלתן או שמיעט במידת חלתן כשרות. Kol haminachot sheriba bemidat challatan o
shemi'eit bemidat challatan k'sherot. Any of the מנחות menachot that you have
more than your ten חלות challos or fewer than your ten חלות
challos is בדיעבד bedi'avad כשרה. kshera. חוץ מלחם הפנים וחביתי כהן גדול.
Chutz milechem hapanim vachavitei kohen gadol. But everything else, including תודה, Toda,
can be less than ten. So that's שמואל Shmuel's opinion: that a
תודה Toda can be fewer than ten and can even really be
just one. And then ויש אומרים, v'yesh omrim, there are those that
say אף לחמי תודה ונזירות, af lachmei toda u-nezirus, even the breads
of תודה Toda and נזירות. nezirus. So, in the end, what do
we say? Is this number מעכב? me'akev? By the לחם הפנים lechem
hapanim and חביתי כהן גדול, chavitei Kohen Gadol, yes, 12. Particularly by
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim we understand. How about לחמי תודה? lachmei toda.
Is that ten מעכב? me'akev? That is a debate. Some say yes,
some say no. I suggest maybe the answer to say that it
is מעכב me'akev is because it's explicit, although as we know explicit
normally doesn't matter. You need it to say something like חוקה. chukah.
So, we'll see in a minute another reason based on the גמרא
Gemara to think that maybe it is the to explain the position
that it's מעכב me'akev by לחמי תודה. lachmei toda So, let's just
finish this. So אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, so רב הונא
Rav Huna says מנחה מאפה, mincha ma'afeh, the oven מנחה, mincha, the
baked מנחה, mincha, שאפאה חלה אחת יצא. she-afah challah achat yatza. If
you didn't do ten, you only did one, you're יוצא. yotzei. Now,
you'd say that's obvious, we just quoted it before. He is not
prepared to say it's true about every מנחה. mincha. He's only prepared
to say that it's true about the oven מנחה. mincha. Why? He's
got a פסוק. pasuk. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason? מצת
כתיב. matzat ketiv. It says the word, it says, you know, what
does it say? וכי תקריב מנחה מנחה מאפה תנור סלת חלות מצות
בלולות בשמן. V'chi takriv mincha mincha ma'afeh tanur solet challot matzot blulot
bashamen. So, it says מצות, matzot, it's without the ו, vav, so
means that בדיעבד bediavad it could be just one מצה. matzah. Okay,
so for him, but he's not willing to say what the ברייתא
Baraita before said, which is that you can have anything can be
fewer, or most things can be fewer; him, it's just by this
because it doesn't have the ו. vav. So מתקיף לה רב פפא,
Matkif lah Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa said to him: that's
not going like the previous ברייתות. Baraitas. טעמא, Ta'ama, your reason is
דכתיב מצת. de-ketiv matzat. It says מצת matzat without the ו. vav.
הא כתיב מצות מנחה מאפה. Ha ketiv matzot mincha ma'afeh. הא כתיב
מצות. Ha ketiv matzot. Had it been written מצות matzot with a
ו, vav, לא, lo, you would say that you could not have
fewer than the full complement. חלות. challot. Okay, it's cross-written. Okay, that's
for the לכתחילה. lechatchila. Okay, so והא גבי לחמי תודה דכתיב מצות.
Ve-ha gabei lachmei toda de-ketiv matzot. By the breads of תודה Toda
it says the word מצות. matzot. ואמר רב טובי בר קיסנא אמר
שמואל לחמי תודה שאפאן ארבע חלות יצא. Ve-amar Rav Tuvi bar Kisna
Amar Shmuel lachmei toda she-afan arba challot yatza. And we said that
the statement of שמואל Shmuel that if you have only ten, if
you have fewer than the ten you're יוצא, yotzei, even though it
says מצות. matzot. So it says פליגא, peliga, that argues on him.
Okay, he doesn't agree with that. Now, the problem is that it's
not only that שמואל Shmuel doesn't agree with him, but the ברייתא
Baraita before said he doesn't agree with any תנא, Tanna, because the
ברייתא Baraita before said that all loaves, all of the ברייתות Baraitas
we quoted said with the exception of לחמי תודה lachmei toda. and
נזיר nazir and לחם הפנים lechem hapanim and the נזירות, nezirus, the
general rule is that all loaves you could do less than the
requisite amount. And he's saying only the מאפה תנור. ma'afeh tanur. So
he's really going against these תנאים. Tannaim. So that's a question. So
תוספות Tosfot actually says: do you understand why they mean you can
do one? No, presumably not. Anyway, I don't know because that maybe
that's so explicit that we don't have to be discussing, I don't
know. But anyway, but תוספות Tosfot says that no, once he says
he really is explaining the position of why you could do fewer
than ten. He is saying that once he says מצת matzat from
the מאפה תנור, ma'afeh tanur, from that then you would extrapolate and
apply it to all the other מנחות, menachos, and there you could
learn that you could do fewer than ten. That's at least the
way תוספות Tosfot tries to reconcile it. But anyway, be that as
it may—I know, I know you don't—anyway, be that as it may,
what do we have? We have that the general rule is ten,
there are some exceptions of twelve, or the reverse, general rule is
twelve, some exceptions of ten, and בדיעבד bediavad if you do really
any amount you're יוצא, yotzei, perhaps again with a few exceptions like
particularly the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, maybe also the לחמי תודה. Okay,
now we are going to go on to finishing up the recipe.
Last one here—well actually not last because it's going to continue into
the next פרק. perek. Anyway, העומר, Ha-omer, we're back to the עומר.
omer. העומר הבא עשרון. Ha-omer ha-ba issaron. Now we're talking about how
much flour, but not so it would be an עשרון issaron of
flour, which we estimated was about a five-pound bag of flour. And
how would you get this עשרון? issaron? משלש סאין, mi-shalosh se'in, from
three סאה se'ah of wheat. How much was three סאה? se'ah? Three
סאה se'ah was basically ten עשרונים. issaronim. Three סאה se'ah is an
איפה. ephah. This will all be important tomorrow. Okay, and an איפה
ephah is—what does the תורה Torah say? The תורה Torah says עשירית
האיפה, asirit ha-ephah, right, עשרון issaron is עשירית האיפה. asirit ha-ephah. So
three סאין se'in make an איפה, ephah, so therefore three סאין se'in
is ten times. So you would start with
ten times the quantity from which you would get your fifty bag
of wheat.
Now again, I don't know, are
we including the
stalks and the husks and whatnot, or are we after you remove
the kernels? I don't know. But you would start—it sounded like the
earlier גמרא Gemara that this was actually the amount harvested and included
the whole stalk and everything—so you would start with ten times the
quantity from which you would get your one עשרון issaron of flour.
שתי הלחם, Shtei halechem, שתי עשרונים shtei esronim משלוש סאים. mishalosh se'im.
The שתי הלחם shtei halechem you would need two עשרונים esronim because
an עשרון isaron per לחם lechem from three סאים. se'im. So again,
you would start by the same amount, but you would get two
עשרונים esronim out of it. So it would be, you know, it
would not be the
proportion would be, the ratio would be half.
So we'll see in the גמרא Gemara why, why it wasn't the
same ratio. לחם הפנים, Lechem hapanim, ולחם הפנים עשרים וארבע עשרונים. v'lechem
hapanim esrim v'arba esronim. Now this is quite interesting. ולחם הפנים V'lechem
hapanim is 12 loaves, but as opposed to the general rule which
a normal thing is an עשרון, isaron, the תורה Torah says by
the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim it's two עשרונות esronos per loaf. So
each loaf is, is much larger. What's the פסוק? pasuk? What? What's
the פסוק pasuk why? I'm not sure, I don't remember offhand. The
פסוק pasuk would be anyway so it's 24 עשרונים. esronim. Now how
much would you do it out of? מעשרים וארבע סאים, Me'esrim v'arba
se'im, from 24 סאים. se'im. So here the ratio would be, as
opposed to before the ratio was ten to one, then when it
got to the שתי הלחם shtei halechem it became five to one,
it was halved, right? Now it's 24 from 24 סאים. se'im. So
if 24 סאים se'im is, the math here should be obvious, but
I'm just trying to, hold on. 24 סאים se'im is three, three
סאים se'im an איפה. eifah. So 24 סאים se'im is eight איפה
eifah and ten עשרונות, esronos, so it's 80, it's 80 עשרונות esronos
to 24. So I don't know, it's not so obvious. Anyway, it's
about, it's a little more like, it's like a little, it's like
three and a quarter proportion to one. So it went from ten
to one ratio for the עומר Omer to five to one for
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and now we're like I think it's
three and a third to one for the לחם הפנים.
lechem hapanim. So the question is why are
the ratios of wheat to flour changing so radically? So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. I mean, there's only so much
flour you can have. I mean, I know, but why the, what's
the ratio of wheat to flour? I mean, you have so much
of it, it's hard to like, you know, demand more of you
maybe. Right, you know, maybe just because of cost. Well, let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara will get to
cost in a minute. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason the
ratio starts high and gets lower? So כיון דמחדשא אתי, keivan d'michadsha
ati, the עומר Omer comes from the new grain, ומשעורין אתי, umise'orin
ati, and from barley. And the assumption is two things: when the
grain is first new and it hasn't been drying out and whatnot,
it's just, it was immediately harvested, there's a lot more of the
bran and the פסולת psolet and whatnot you have to get rid
of. If you've let it dry out in the fields, like a
lot of the gunk I guess dries away and falls away. So
number one, there's a lot more that has to be filtered out.
And number two, barley apparently has a lot more פסולת, psolet, dross,
or whatever it's called, hulls and whatever than wheat. So because it's
new and it's
barley, you're going to need
a ten to one ratio in order to get your עשרון isaron
at the end. Okay. עשרון מובחר לא אתי, Isaron muvchar lo ati,
you don't get a nice עשרון isaron of like sifted fine flour,
אלא משלש סאים, ela mishalosh se'im, except from three סאים, se'im, which
as I said is a ten to one ratio. שתי הלחם שתי
עשרונות משלש סאים. Shtei halechem shtei esronos mishalosh se'im. שתי הלחם, Shtei
halechem, it's half of the ratio, it's a five to one, two
עשרונות esronos from three סאים. se'im. So כיון דמחיטין אתיין, keivan d'michitin
atyan, so it's coming from wheat. אף על גב דמחדשא אתיין, Af
al gav d'michadsha atyan, although it's newly harvested, so on the one
hand newly harvested there's a lot of, there is a lot of
hulls and whatnot, on the other hand it's wheat, which does not,
which is apparently a better ratio. So therefore we can halve the
ratio. שתי עשרונות אתו משלש סאים. Shtei esronos atu mishalosh se'im. You
can get your two עשרונות esronos from your three סאים se'im which
as I said is a five to one ratio. לחם הפנים. Lechem
hapanim. Now the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, עשרים וארבע עשרונות מעשרים וארבע
סאים, esrim v'arba esronos me'esrim v'arba se'im, 24 from 24 סאים. se'im.
Now that's, so but again, the ratio is as I said about
three and a third to one, so that's even less. Why? מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Because you have two things going for it: כיון
דמחיטין אתו, keivan d'michitin atu, number one it's wheat, which you need
a lesser ratio, ומישן אתו, umiyashan atu, it's coming from grain that's
been dried out. Right, whatever time in the year you bring the
לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, you can always bring it from the older
grain, you don't have to bring
it from grain that you just harvested. And if you're bringing it
from the older grain and it's been drying out, then the, the,
you know, the ratio of grain to flour is going to be
high, lower. So therefore, עשרון מובחר אתי מסאה, isaron muvchar ati mise'ah,
you can get even a good עשרון isaron just from a סאה,
se'ah, from a like three and a third to one ratio, you
do not need such a high ratio in order to get to.
So interestingly, he's saying don't get confused, which I would have, from
the משנה Mishnah
to think that the maybe there's a higher standard of the quality
of flour for the עומר. Omer. That's what you would think. If
the ratio is higher, there's a higher quality of flour. No, it's
just the raw product requires a bigger ratio to get the same
end result. Now the other thing to know is which is is
that the, you know, in all of these things, we're saying oh,
one עשרון isaron of an עומר, Omer, two עשרונות esronos for the
שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, you know, for one per bread, two עשרונות
esronos for the, for the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. But although we
normally talk about עשרון, isaron, how you're using the עשרון isaron is
very different. By a normal מנחה, mincha, we say you take one
עשרון isaron and you break it up into ten loaves, right? That's
what we said before, you have ten loaves. Here, by the שתי
הלחם, shtei halechem, we're saying that each loaf or by, you know...
is two עשרונות. isronot. Each loaf of the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
is twice the amount of all of your ten loaves of your
מנחה. mincha. And you're understanding this? The עשרון isaron of the מנחה
mincha is one עשרון, isaron, one bag of flour that you divide
into ten loaves. By the שתי הלחם shtei halechem you use two
bags of—I'm not saying bags—let's say לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, use two
bags of flour for each individual loaf, okay? Or for the עומר
omer you use one bag of flour for, for the one עומר.
omer. Or for the שתי הלחם shtei halechem you use one bag
of flour for each of the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. So by
the מנחה mincha that makes sense. One bag of flour you divide
it into ten loaves, but for these other things, you know, it's
the same bag of flour but they're being in one much, much
larger loaf for these types of things. Okay.
So now let's take a look at the—let's finish this up. Summary
sandwiches. What? תנו רבנן. Tana Rabanan.
Our rabbis taught:
כל המנחות שריבה במדת עשרונם או שמיעט במדת עשרונם פסולות. Kol hamnachot
she'riba b'midat isronam o she'mi'et b'midat isronam psulot.
Let's
say you did not have your exact עשרון. isaron. Let's say you
had more than an עשרון isaron of flour or less than an
עשרון isaron of flour, then it would be invalid. You have to
have the exact right amount. ריבה במדת סאים שלהן או שמיעט במדת
סאים שלהן כשרות. Riba b'midat se'im shelahen o she'mi'et b'midat se'im shelahen
kesherot. This
almost is obvious. If you started with more of the wheat or
less of the wheat, if in the end you wound up with
the same עשרון, isaron, you're okay. You know, these ratios are the
appropriate ratios to get the fine flour at the end. But if
you started with less wheat and got less fine flour or more
wheat and got even more flour, that's not מעכב. ma'akev. What is
מעכב ma'akev is that you have that עשרון, isaron, the exact amount
when you're making the מנחה. mincha. Okay, now let's take a look
at the—last system two more times. Right, that's also possible. But presumably
even if the quality of the flour was a little less than
ideal, you would still be יוצא. yotzei. Okay, let's look now at
the next משנה. mishna. If the quality was less than ideal, I
would have thought because you just sifted... But it never says that
it's בדיעבד b'di'avad מעכב. ma'akev. Okay, so let's take a look at
the next משנה. mishna. העומר היה מנופת בשלש עשרה נפה. Ha'omer haya
munafat b'shlosha asar nafa. Now it's talking about how you actually—now we
know the amount of
wheat you start with and we talked about I
guess rubbing the wheat before. Now we're going to
talk about the actual siftings
that you do. So the עומר omer they would sift with thirteen
sieves. And as we learned, you know, because you start with more
bran with the עומר, omer, it needed to be sifted more to
get the same quality. שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, the שתי הלחם בשנים
עשר, shtei halechem b'shnaim asar, you could use only one fewer sieve,
only twelve. ולחם הפנים, V'lechem hapanim, the לחם הפנים באחד עשר, lechem
hapanim b'achad asar, eleven sieves. Now again, it's a little funny. If
there's so much great difference between the amount of wheat, the whole
difference with the sieves is one, you know, it seems much more
symbolic. I really don't know the explanation. It does seem much more
symbolic. The גמרא Gemara doesn't explain it.
Did they use
the actual number of sieves or could it be done 13, 12,
11 times?
Well no, we're going to actually see that the sieves were changing
of size of the hole so that each process of sifting got
out something the previous process did not get out. Right.
And especially also since one of—since the last two, the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem and then לחם הפנים lechem hapanim are both wheat, so
you know you'd think it'd be the same number of sieves.
Yeah, but the גמרא Gemara says again that the לחם הפנים lechem
hapanim came from older grain so it required less. That was the
whole point of previous גמרא, Gemara, but still, there's a much bigger
difference in the amount of wheat you start with than the amount
of sieves that you have. The other thing that's to note here
is what's the story about a standard מנחה? mincha? How much about
a standard—how much do I, you know, start with with the standard
מנחה? mincha? How many sieves do I need? It actually seems like
that there's less of an insistence there about a particular ratio and
you could even just bring whatever flour you happen to have in
your house. But these things that are communal sacrifices, we want it
to be much more on top of exactly how the whole procedure
was done. But there's a sense that there's much more latitude when
it comes to your own personal מנחה. mincha. It has to be
סולת, solet, but exactly that we should dictate how much wheat it
has to start with, how many sieves you have to use, that
we're not saying. Okay, so... It's very relevant given the differences also.
Well, right, although presumably for a קרבן korban you'd want to have
some standard. Okay, so now it says like this. Okay, ולחם הפנים
אחד עשר. v'lechem hapanim achad asar. רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer,
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says, לא היה להן קצבה אלא סולת מנופה
כל צרכה היה מביא. lo haya lahen kitzva ela solet menufa kol
tzorcha haya mevi. That's a pretty reasonable answer. There was not a
fixed number, 13, 12, 11. You had to have finely sifted flour,
whatever it takes. שנאמר, Shenemar, the פסוק pasuk says, ולקחת סולת ואפית
אותה. v'lakachta solet v'afita ota.
You shall take סולת solet and you shall bake it.
So עד שתהא מנופה, ad she'teh menufa, there's a little play on
the word ואפית. afita. ואפית afita means bake but also מנופה menufa
which means sifting כל צרכה kol tzorcha as much as you need
it.
So whatever's needed, you sift it. There's no certain number.
It shows a logical approach. Yes. תנו רבנן. Tana Rabanan. So let's
wrap this up. Our rabbis taught: Here is the order in which
you do the sifting: בדקה בגסה בדקה בגסה. b'daka b'gasa b'daka b'gasa.
You alternate a thin sieve and a thick one. And the way
רש"י Rashi explains and actually will come out in the next statement
of רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר
Rebbi
Shimon
ben
Elazar
is that they work differently because the question always with sifting is
what are you trying to retain and what are you trying to
get rid of? Are you trying to do the sift so that
the bad stuff falls through and you the... When you have a
flour sifter, the bad stuff stays behind, oh same, bad stuff stays
behind and the flour goes through. Not necessarily. I mean, I thought
that at least the way Hirsch explains it, and based on some
other Gemaras, that what you're trying to do is you're trying to
get like the nice thick grain
so that you can have, okay, so that I don't know, that's
interesting.
Yeah, so
anyway maybe the grains as opposed to the flour. So what Rashi
says is, that's the difference between the thin sieve and the thick
sieve. The thin sieve, you're trying to get rid of the, like
the very thin פסולת, psolet, the very thin
dust or whatever. So it's so thin that the flour, the grains
you want to retain doesn't go through and only the sand and
all of that stuff, you know, gets goes out, right? If you're
trying to get out the sand, let's assume that there's sand mixed
up. How do you do it? You have a thin sieve that
sand will go through but the flour grains won't go through. So
that's the purpose of the thin sieves. The purpose of the thick
sieves is the opposite. It's you have like the bran. After the
bran has separated out, so you want the hole big enough to
let the grain go through but not so big that the bran
goes through, the bran stays above. So the
big holes are to keep the פסולת psolet above and the small
holes are to make the פסולת psolet go down. And you would
alternate, Rashi and the way Rashi explains it is that the size
of the holes would constantly be converging, the big holes would be
getting smaller and the small holes would be getting bigger. You can
figure it out, it works. Anyway so that at each level you're
sifting out something more than you sifted out before. Okay so doesn't
two of
them just go back and forth?
No, no, no, no, the each one has a different sized hole
so that let's imagine for example the wide one where I'm getting
rid of the bran. So it was a certain width, the bran
went through, but only big bran, excuse me, if it was very
wide how would it work?
The bran goes through, yeah,
wide
enough to keep this bran on top and the husk or something
like that.
No, no, no, no, no, if it's big, the grain is going
through. No, I'm sorry I got it backward. If it's big, the
grain is going through and the big grain is staying above, but
the smaller bran went down with the grain. So to get that
you're going to need another one which is a little bit smaller
hole. Okay so you keep on changing the sizes so that more
and more gets sifted out. Okay. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rebbi
Shimon ben Elazar omer, Rebbi Shimon Elazar says, שלושה עשר נפות היו
במקדש, shlosha asar nefot hayu bamikdash, there were thirteen. Now this is
not like Rebbi Shimon in the Mishnah, Rebbi Shimon Elazar is a
different Rebbi Shimon, there were thirteen which is the author of our
Mishnah, זו למעלה מזו וזו למעלה מזו, zu lemala mizu vezu lemala
mizu, each one above, whatever that means, I'll say in a minute,
the other, עליונה קולטת סובין ותחתונה קולטת סולת. elyona koletet subin vetachtona
koletet solet. The first one catches the bran, which means it had
the big holes so the grain went down and the bran stayed
above. The bottom one catches the flour, which means that it had
the small hole, the flour stayed above and the small little dirt
or whatever came out below. So some want to say and I
think it's a reasonable read of Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar that he
doesn't, no, no, well but yes, but he doesn't have this whole
idea of alternating thin and thick, thin and thick. He actually just
what he says זו למעלה מזו, zu lemala mizu, he meant the
biggest holes on the top slowly getting smaller to the smallest hole
below and that's how he would do it rather than alternating big
holes and small holes and then eventually you'd have flour left at
the bottom with the פסולת psolet of, whether that really works in
terms of the order in which you have to sift, I don't
know, I've never done this before. Yeah, would it be like a
big container, different levels, you pour the, I don't, yeah, it's not
an automatic thing. In order to sift well you gotta shake it
and work, it requires elbow grease, yeah, nothing is automatic, no. Okay
so let's just, okay so let's yeah, let's just finish up here.
Okay, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר מלועין וקינצוס,
amar Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar melo'in vekintzos, Rebbi Shimon ben Elazar just
says, just do a good job, he doesn't matter if it's thirteen
or what's the number. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, סולת ועשית, solet ve'asita,
flour and you should bake it, אותה, ota, מלמד שנקראת סולת, melamed
shenikret solet, you can purchase straight flour from the marketplace. ומנין שאפילו
חטים, uminayin she'afilu chitin, how do you know you can even purchase
the wheat from the marketplace? תלמוד לומר ולקחת, talmud lomar velakachta, you
can purchase, you take it. So let's actually just take a look
at the פסוק pasuk itself for one second because this is actually
quite interesting in terms of
the difference between, you know, what was sort of required. This is
ויקרא כד. Vayikra chaf dalet. So this is I think by the
Omer, if I remember correctly, what else would be in ויקרא כד?
Vayikra chaf dalet? Oh no, I'm sorry, it's the לחם הפנים. lechem
hapanim. Okay so, oh it's the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Right, I'm
sorry, yeah, of course because that's the end of the Mishnah as
we'll see in a minute, it's about the amount of לחם הפנים.
lechem hapanim. So it says like this, it says here and here's
the שני עשרונים shnei esronim Michael, it says ולקחת סולת ואפית אותה
שתים עשרה חלות, velakachta solet ve'afita ota shteim esreh chalot, there's twelve
chalot, it's explicit, שני עשרונים יהיה החלה האחת. shnei esronim yihyeh hachalah
ha'achat. Okay, so it says ולקחת סולת ואפית אותה שתים עשרה חלות
velakachta solet ve'afita ota shteim esreh chalot and this is by the
לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. So, so first of all you can purchase
the סולת solet from the... at the marketplace, then you don't have
to sift it, you don't have to do the sifting, but presumably,
and again this is what רש"י Rashi says, you know, presumably you
can trust somebody else that the sifting needs to be done, but
you can trust somebody else to do this and we had this
before. This is a shocking thing, like you know, especially now you
know, everything has to be משגיח תמידי mashgiach tmidi and so on,
particularly in the מקדש. Mikdash. We had before you can, you know,
a קרבן korban needs to be checked four days before for מום,
mum, you can buy it from a middleman, from you know, from
a retailer, and he tells you that he's checked it for four
days. You can actually, you know, you don't have to do that
in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. And here we're finding something very
similar. You can go ahead and presumably it still needs the sifting
that we just discussed, but you can purchase it from somebody. You
don't have to do it yourself. Well, you can see, I mean,
you can see the results. You can see the results, that's true.
That is true. Okay, if you really needed thirteen, you couldn't necessarily
see the thirteen, but yes. Okay, ומניין שאפילו חיטים,
u'minayin
she'afillu
chitin, how do you know you can even buy wheat, which is
surprising, like why would I think you couldn't? Right, meaning grain which
hasn't been sifted on your own. Buy wheat and sift them on
your own. תלמוד לומר ולקחתם, Talmud lomar u'lekachtem, מכל מקום. mikol makom.
You can purchase I don't know, he somehow breaks off the word
סולת. solet. You can get it even when it's wheat. יכול אף
בשאר מנחות כן, yachol af bish'ar menachot ken, maybe other מנחות menachot
you can purchase wheat and you don't have to purchase as opposed
to purchasing flour, תלמוד לומר אותה, Talmud lomar otah, it. מפני החיסכון,
mipnei hachisachon, because of the חיסכון. chisachon. What the heck is that?
מאי מפני החיסכון, mai mipnei hachisachon, what does that mean? אמר רבי
אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, התורה חסה על ממונם של ישראל, Hatorah chasah
al mamonam shel Yisrael, the Torah is concerned about the cost. If
you buy flour, right, especially if it has to be thirteen times
processed, they're going to charge a very high premium. And think about
the previous משנה, Mishnah, think how much
flour went into the, to the לחם הפנים. Lechem HaPanim.
The לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim was twenty-four עשרונים, esronim, it was a
huge amount and it was every week, right? So it was twenty-four
bags of flour, you know, with the special בד"ץ Badatz הכשר hechsher
and שמורה משעת הקצירה. shmurah misheat haktzirah. So, you know, that's, think
how much you pay for matzah. So with that, it's going to
cost a lot of money.
So because it would cost so much money, because you need such
a large quantity on such a regular basis, you're allowed to buy
the wheat and you can do the process yourself. But every other
מנחה mincha you have to buy the flour? So I have to
tell you, I don't understand this exactly. What, a normal מנחה, mincha,
I'm not allowed to do it myself in the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, I have to ask somebody else to do? I really don't
understand, unless somehow there's a point that, you know, oh no, that's
too mundane activity, that shouldn't be the business of the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. Let somebody else do the grind... No no, but we,
we in the, we're here talking in the context of communal קרבנות.
korbanot. Oh, not my own מנחה, mincha, is it? I don't know.
You're right. It sounds like even regular מנחות menachot not that way.
So I really don't understand this. Why all of a sudden should
I not be allowed to make the flour myself? If it's communal
קרבנות, korbanot, maybe saying it's not appropriate for the מקדש, Mikdash, but
I honestly don't understand it. Anyway, היכא רמיזא, heicha ramiza, where's this
idea that the Torah is concerned for our monetary expenditures, you know,
that we shouldn't waste money? דכתיב והשקית את העדה ואת בעירם. d'chtiv
vehishkita et ha'eda ve'et be'iram. So you shall, you know, cause the
congregation to drink. God says to Moshe, right? So we have to
be concerned with the, you know, with the property of fellows.
Obviously we laugh, but this is a very important principle in הלכה.
halacha. הלכה halacha is very often allowed to adopt more lenient positions
because of concerns about הפסד. hefsed. So this does play very importantly
in other areas of הלכה. halacha.